<!--
  Copyright (c) 2016 OpenPOWER Foundation
  
  Licensed under the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3;
  with no Invariants Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts,
  and with no Back-Cover Texts (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl-1.3.txt

-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Object Files</title>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_97607">
    <title>ELF Header</title>
    <para>The file class member of the ELF header identification array,
    e_ident[EI_CLASS], identifies the ELF file as 64-bit encoded by holding the
    value ELFCLASS64.</para>
    <para>For a big-endian encoded ELF file, the data encoding member of the
    ELF header identification array, e_ident[EI_DATA], holds the value 2,
    defined as data encoding ELFDATA2MSB. For a little-endian encoded ELF file,
    it holds the value 1, defined as data encoding ELFDATA2LSB.</para>
    <programlisting>e_ident[EI_CLASS]    ELFCLASS64   For all 64-bit implementations.
e_ident[EI_DATA]     ELFDATA2MSB  For all big-endian implementations.
e_ident[EI_DATA]     ELFDATA2LSB  For all little-endian implementations.</programlisting>
    <para>The ELF header's e_flags member holds bit flags associated with the
    file. The 64-bit PowerPC processor family defines the following
    flags.</para>
    <para>E_flags defining the ABI level:</para>
    <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="10*" />
        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="90*" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>0</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>For ELF object files of an unspecified nature.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>For the Power ELF V1 ABI using function descriptors. This
              ABI is currently only used for big-endian PowerPC
              implementations.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>2</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>For the OpenPOWER ELF V2 ABI using the facilities described
              here and including function pointers to directly reference
              functions.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>The ABI version to be used for the ELF header file is specified with
    the .abiversion pseudo-op:</para>
    <programlisting>.abiversion 2</programlisting>
    <para>Processor identification resides in the ELF header's e_machine
    member, and must have the value EM_PPC64, defined as the value 21.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Special Sections</title>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_64556" /> lists the sections that are used
    in the Power Architecture to hold program and control information. It also
    shows their types and attributes.</para>
    <para> </para>
    <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_64556">
      <title>Special Sections</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="15*" />
        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="50*" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Section Name</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Attributes</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>.got</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHT_PROGBITS</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHF_ALLOC + SHF_WRITE</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>.toc</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHT_PROGBITS</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHF_ALLOC + SHF_WRITE</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>.plt<footnote>
                 <para>The type of the OpenPOWER ABI .plt section is
                    SHT_NOBITS, not SHT_PROGBITS as on most other processors.</para>
              </footnote></para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHT_NOBITS</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHF_ALLOC + SHF_WRITE</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>.sdata</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHT_PROGBITS</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHF_ALLOC + SHF_WRITE</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>.sbss</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHT_NOBITS</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHF_ALLOC + SHF_WRITE</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>.data1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHT_PROGBITS</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHF_ALLOC + SHF_WRITE</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>.bss1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHT_NOBITS</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SHF_ALLOC + SHF_WRITE</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>Suggested uses of these special sections follow:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The .got section may hold the Global Offset Table (GOT). This
        section is not normally present in a relocatable object file because it
        is linker generated. The linker must ensure that .got is aligned to an
        8-byte boundary. In an executable or shared library, it may contain
        part or all of the TOC. For more information, see
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655240___RefHeading___Toc377640591" /> and 
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655242_47739" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The .toc section may hold the initialized TOC. The .toc section
        must be aligned to an 8-byte boundary. Address elements within .toc
        must be aligned to 8-byte boundaries to support linker optimization of
        the .toc section. In a relocatable object file, .toc may contain
        addresses of objects and functions; in this respect it may be thought
        of as a compiler-managed GOT. It may also contain other constants or
        variables; in this respect it is like .sdata. In an executable or
        shared library, it may contain part or the entirety of the TOC. For
        more information, see
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_66700" />, 
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655240___RefHeading___Toc377640591" />, and 
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655242_47739" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The .plt section may hold the procedure linkage table. This
        section is not normally present in a relocatable object file because it
        is linker generated. Each entry within the .plt section is an 8-byte
        address. The linker must ensure that .plt is aligned to an 8-byte
        boundary. For more information, see
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655242_20388" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The .sdata section may hold initialized small-sized data. For
        more information, see
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_81959" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The .sbss section may hold uninitialized small-sized data.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The .data1 section may hold initialized medium-sized data.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The .bss1 section may hold uninitialized medium-sized
        data.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Tools that support this ABI are not required to use these sections.
    However, if a tool uses these sections, it must assign the types and
    attributes specified in 
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_64556" />. Tools are not required to use
    the sections precisely as suggested. Relocation information and the code
    that refers to it define the actual use of a section.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_66700">
    <title>TOC</title>
    <para>The TOC is part of the data segment of an executable program.</para>
    <para>This section describes a common layout of the TOC in an executable
    file or shared object. Particular tools are not required to follow the
    layout specified here.</para>
    <para>The TOC region commonly includes data items within the .got, .toc,
    .sdata, and .sbss sections. In the medium code model, they can be addressed
    with 32-bit signed offsets from the TOC pointer register. The TOC pointer
    register typically points to the beginning of the .got section + 0x8000,
    which permits a 2 GB TOC with the medium and large code models. The .got
    section is typically created by the link editor based on @got relocations.
    The .toc section is typically included from relocatable object files
    referenced during the link phase.</para>
    <para>The TOC may straddle the boundary between initialized and
    uninitialized data in the data segment. The common order of sections in the
    data segment, some of which may be empty, follows:</para>
    <programlisting>.rodata
.data
.data1
.got
.toc
.sdata
.sbss
.plt
.bss1
.bss</programlisting>
    <para>The medium code model is expected to provide a sufficiently large TOC
    to provide all data addressing needs of a module with a single TOC.</para>
    <para>Compilers may generate two-instruction medium code model references
    (or, if selected, short displacement one-instruction references) for all
    data items that are in the TOC for the object file being compiled. Such
    references are relative to the TOC pointer register, r2. (The linker may
    optimize two-instruction forms to one instruction forms, replacing a first
    instruction of the two instruction form with a nop and rewriting the second
    instruction. Consequently, the TOC pointer must be live during the first
    and second instruction of a two-instruction reference.)</para>
    <para>&#160;</para>
    <bridgehead>Modules Containing Multiple TOCs</bridgehead>
    <para>The link editor may create multiple TOCs. In such a case, the
    constituent .got, .toc, .sdata, and .sbss sections are conceptually
    repeated as necessary, with each TOC typically using a TOC pointer value
    of its base plus 0x8000. Any constituent section of type SHT_NOBITS in
    any TOC but the last is converted to type SHT_PROGBITS filled with
    zeros.</para>
    <para>When multiple TOCs are present, linking must take care to save,
    initialize, and restore TOC pointers within a single module when calling
    from one function to a second function using a different TOC pointer
    value. Many of the same issues associated with a cross-module call apply
    also to calls within a module but using different TOC pointers.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_73385">
    <title>Symbol Table</title>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_95185">
      <title>Symbol Values</title>
      <para>An executable file that contains a symbol reference that is to be
      resolved dynamically by an associated shared object will have a symbol
      table entry for that symbol. This entry will identify the symbol as
      undefined by setting the st_shndx member to SHN_UNDEF.</para>
      <para>The OpenPOWER ABI uses the three most-significant bits in the
      symbol st_other field to specify the number of instructions between a
      function's global entry point and local entry point. The global entry
      point is used when it is necessary to set up the TOC pointer (r2) for the
      function. The local entry point is used when r2 is known to already be
      valid for the function. A value of zero in these bits asserts that the
      function does not use r2.</para>
      <para>The values of these three most significant bits of the st_other
      field have the following meanings:</para>
      <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="10*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="90*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The local and global entry points are the same, and the
                function has a single entry point with no requirement on r12 or
                r2. On return, r2 will contain the same value as at
                entry.</para>
                <para>This value should be used for functions that do not
                require the use of a TOC register to access external data. In
                particular, functions that do not access data through the TOC
                pointer can use a common entry point for the local and global
                entry points.</para>
                <note>
                  <para>If the function is not a leaf function, it must
                  call subroutines using the R_PPC64_REL24_NOTOC relocation
                  to indicate that the TOC register is not initialized. In
                  turn, this may lead to more expensive procedure linkage
                  table (PLT) stub code than would be necessary if a TOC
                  register were initialized.</para>
                </note>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The local and global entry points are the same, and r2
                should be treated as caller-saved for local and global
                callers.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The local entry point is at one instruction past the
                global entry point.</para>
                <para>When called at the global entry point, r12 must be set to
                the function entry address. r2 will be set to the TOC base that
                this function needs, so it must be preserved and restored by
                the caller.</para>
                <para>When called at the local entry point, r12 is not used and
                r2 must already point to the TOC base that this function needs,
                and it will be preserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The local entry point is at two instructions past the
                global entry point.</para>
                <para>When called at the global entry point, r12 must be set to
                the function entry address. r2 will be set to the TOC base that
                this function needs, so it must be preserved and restored by
                the caller.</para>
                <para>When called at the local entry point, r12 is not used and
                r2 must already point to the TOC base that this function needs,
                and it will be preserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The local entry point is at four instructions past the
                global entry point.</para>
                <para>When called at the global entry point, r12 must be set to
                the function entry address. r2 will be set to the TOC base that
                this function needs, so it must be preserved and restored by
                the caller.</para>
                <para>When called at the local entry point, r12 is not used and
                r2 must already point to the TOC base that this function needs,
                and it will be preserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The local entry point is at eight instructions past the
                global entry point.</para>
                <para>When called at the global entry point, r12 must be set to
                the function entry address. r2 will be set to the TOC base that
                this function needs, so it must be preserved and restored by
                the caller.</para>
                <para>When called at the local entry point, r12 is not used and
                r2 must already point to the TOC base that this function needs,
                and it will be preserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The local entry point is at 16 instructions past the
                global entry point.</para>
                <para>When called at the global entry point, r12 must be set to
                the function entry address. r2 will be set to the TOC base that
                this function needs, so it must be preserved and restored by
                the caller.</para>
                <para>When called at the local entry point, r12 is not used and
                r2 must already point to the TOC base that this function needs,
                and it will be preserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>7</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Reserved</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>The local-entry-point handling field of st_other is generated with
      the .localentry pseudo op:</para>
      <programlisting revisionflag="changed">    .globl my_func
    .type my_func, @function
my_func:
    addis r2, r12, my_sym@ha(.TOC.-my_func)
    addi r2, r2, my_sym@l(.TOC.-my_func)
    .localentry my_func, .-my_func
    ... ; function definition
    blr</programlisting>
      <para>Functions called via symbols with an st_other value of 0 may be
      called without a valid TOC pointer in r2. Symbols of functions that
      require a local entry with a valid TOC pointer should generate a symbol
      with an st_other field value of 2 - 6 and both local and global entry
      points, even if the global entry point will not be used. (In such a case,
      the instructions of the global entry setup sequence may optionally be
      initialized with TRAP instructions.)</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_81959">
      <title>Use of the Small Data Area</title>
      <para>For a data item in the .sdata or .sbss sections, a compiler may
      generate short-form one-instruction references. In an executable file or
      shared library, such a reference is relative to the address of the TOC
      base symbol (which can be obtained from r2 if a TOC pointer is
      initialized). A compiler that generates code using the small data area
      should provide an option to select the maximum size of objects placed in
      the small data area, and a means of disabling any use of the small data
      area. When generating code for ELF shared libraries, the small data area
      should not be used for default-visibility global objects. This is to
      satisfy ELF shared-library symbol interposition rules. That is, an
      ordinary global symbol in a shared library may be overridden by a symbol
      of the same name defined in the executable or another shared library.
      Supporting interposition when using TOC-pointer relative addressing would
      require text relocations.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_18894">
    <title>Relocation Types</title>
    <para>The relocation entries in a relocatable file are used by the link
    editor to transform the contents of that file into an executable file or a
    shared object file. The application and result of a relocation are similar
    for both. Several relocatable files may be combined into one output file.
    The link editor merges the content of the files, sets the value of all
    function symbols, and performs relocations.</para>
    <para>The 64-bit OpenPOWER Architecture uses Elf64_Rela relocation entries
    exclusively. A relocation entry may operate upon a halfword, word, or
    doubleword. The r_offset member of the relocation entry designates the
    first byte of the address affected by the relocation. The subfield of
    r_offset affected by a relocation is implicit in the definition of the
    applied relocation type. The r_addend member of the relocation entry serves
    as the relocation addend, which is described in 
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_45722" /> for each relocation type.</para>
    <para>A relocation type defines a set of instructions and calculations
    necessary to alter the subfield data of a particular relocation
    field.</para>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_45722">
      <title>Relocation Fields</title>
      <para>The following relocation fields identify a subfield of an address
      affected by a relocation.</para>
      <para>Bit numbers are shown at the bottom of the boxes. (Only big-endian
      bit numbers are shown for space considerations.) Byte numbers are shown
      in the top of the boxes; big-endian byte numbers are displayed in the
      upper left corners and little-endian in the upper right corners. The byte
      order specified in a relocatable fileâ€™s ELF header applies to all the
      elements of a relocation entry, the relocation field definitions, and
      relocation type calculations.</para>
      <para>In the following figure, doubleword64 specifies a 64-bit field
      occupying 8 bytes, the alignment of which is 8 bytes unless otherwise
      specified.</para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="8">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="12*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>7</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>4</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry nameend="c8" namest="c1" align="center">
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>7</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry nameend="c8" namest="c1" align="center">
                <para>doubleword64 (continued)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>63</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para> </para>
      <para> </para>
      <para>In the following figure, word32 specifies a 32-bit field taking up
      4 bytes and maintaining 4-byte alignment unless otherwise
      indicated.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="8">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="12*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry nameend="c8" namest="c1" align="center">
                <para>word32</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>31</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>In the following figure, word30 specifies a 30-bit field taking up
      bits 0 - 29 of a word and maintaining 4-byte alignment unless otherwise
      indicated.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="32">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c9" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c10" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c11" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c12" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c13" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c14" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c15" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c16" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c17" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c18" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c19" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c20" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c21" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c22" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c23" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c24" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c25" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c26" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c27" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c28" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c29" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c30" colwidth="3*" colsep="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c31" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c32" colwidth="3*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry nameend="c30" namest="c1" align="center" colsep="1">
                <para>word30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>29</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>31</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>In the following figure, low24 specifies a 24-bit field taking up
      bits 6 - 29 of a word and maintaining 4-byte alignment. The other bits
      remain unchanged. A call or unconditional branch instruction is an
      example of this field.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="32">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="3*" colsep="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c9" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c10" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c11" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c12" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c13" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c14" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c15" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c16" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c17" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c18" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c19" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c20" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c21" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c22" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c23" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c24" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c25" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c26" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c27" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c28" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c29" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c30" colwidth="3*" colsep="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c31" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c32" colwidth="3*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colsep="1">
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry nameend="c30" namest="c10" colsep="1" align="center">
                <para>low24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>29</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>31</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>In the following figure, low21 specifies a 21-bit field occupying
      the least-significant bits of a word with 4-byte alignment.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="32">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c9" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c10" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c11" colwidth="3*" colsep="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c12" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c13" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c14" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c15" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c16" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c17" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c18" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c19" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c20" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c21" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c22" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c23" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c24" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c25" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c26" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c27" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c28" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c29" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c30" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c31" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c32" colwidth="3*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry nameend="c32" namest="c12" colsep="1" align="center">
                <para>low21</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>10</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>11</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>31</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>In the following figure, low14 specifies a 14-bit field taking up
      bits 16 - 29 and possibly bit 10 (the branch prediction bit) of a word
      and maintaining 4-byte alignment. The other bits remain unchanged. A
      conditional branch instruction is an example usage.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="32">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c9" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c10" colwidth="3*" colsep="1" />
          <colspec colname="c11" colwidth="3*" colsep="1" />
          <colspec colname="c12" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c13" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c14" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c15" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c16" colwidth="3*" colsep="1" />
          <colspec colname="c17" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c18" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c19" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c20" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c21" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c22" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c23" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c24" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c25" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c26" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c27" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c28" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c29" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c30" colwidth="3*" colsep="1" />
          <colspec colname="c31" colwidth="3*" />
          <colspec colname="c32" colwidth="3*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry nameend="c30" namest="c17" align="center">
                <para>low14</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>10</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>15</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>29</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>31</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>In the following figure, half16 specifies a 16-bit field taking up
      two bytes and maintaining 2-byte alignment. The immediate field of an Add
      Immediate instruction is an example of this field.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <?dbhtml table-width="50%" ?>
        <?dbfo table-width="50%" ?>        
        <tgroup cols="16">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c9" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c10" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c11" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c12" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c13" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c14" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c15" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c16" colwidth="6*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry nameend="c16" namest="c1" align="center">
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>7</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>8</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>9</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>10</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>11</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>12</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>13</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>14</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>15</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>In the following figure, half16ds is similar to half16, but is
      really just 14 bits because the two least-significant bits must be zero
      and are not really part of the field. (Used by, for example, the ldu
      instruction.) In addition to the use of this relocation field with the DS
      forms, half16ds relocations are also used in conjunction with DQ forms.
      In those instances, the linker and assembler collaborate to create valid
      DQ forms. They raise an error if the specified offset does not meet the
      constraints of a valid DQ instruction form displacement.</para>
      <informaltable frame="all" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <?dbhtml table-width="50%" ?>
        <?dbfo table-width="50%" ?>        
        <tgroup cols="16">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c8" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c9" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c10" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c11" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c12" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c13" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c14" colwidth="6*" colsep="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c15" colwidth="6*" />
          <colspec colname="c16" colwidth="6*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right" colsep="1">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry nameend="c14" namest="c1" align="center">
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>7</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>8</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>9</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>10</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>11</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>12</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>13</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>14</para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="right">
                <para>15</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_51269">
      <title>Relocation Notations</title>
      <para>The following notations are used in the relocation table.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="80*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>A</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the addend used to compute the value of the
                relocatable field.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>B</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the base address at which a shared object file
                has been loaded into memory during execution. Generally, a
                shared object file is built with a 0 base virtual address, but
                the execution address will be different. See Program Header in
                the System V ABI for more information about the base
                address.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>G</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the offset from .TOC. at which the address of
                the relocation entryâ€™s symbol resides during execution. This
                implies the creation of a .got section. For more information,
                see 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655240___RefHeading___Toc377640591" /> and
                
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655242_47739" />.</para>
                <para>Reference in a calculation to the value G implicitly
                creates a GOT entry for the indicated symbol.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>L</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the section offset or address of the procedure
                linkage table entry for the symbol. This implies the creation
                of a .plt section if one does not already exist. It also
                implies the creation of a procedure linkage table (PLT) entry
                for resolving the symbol. For an unresolved symbol, the PLT
                entry points to a PLT resolver stub. For a resolved symbol, a
                procedure linkage table entry holds the final effective address
                of a dynamically resolved symbol (see 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655242_20388" />).</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>M</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Similar to G, except that the address that is stored may
                be the address of the procedure linkage table entry for the
                symbol.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>P</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the place (section offset or address) of the
                storage unit being relocated (computed using r_offset).</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the offset of the symbol within the section in
                which the symbol is defined (its section-relative
                address).</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>S</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the value of the symbol whose index resides in
                the relocation entry.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>+</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Denotes 64-bit modulus addition.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>-</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Denotes 64-bit modulus subtraction.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>&gt;&gt;</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Denotes arithmetic right-shifting.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(value)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Denotes the least-significant 16 bits of the indicated
                value. That is:</para>
                <para>#lo(x) = (x &amp; 0xffff).</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(value)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Denotes bits 16 - 63 of the indicated value. That
                is:</para>
                <para>#hi(x) = x &gt;&gt; 16</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(value)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Denotes the high adjusted value: bits 16 - 63 of the
                indicated value, compensating for #lo( ) being treated as a
                signed number. That is:</para>
                <para>#ha(x) = (x + 0x8000) &gt;&gt; 16</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>TP</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The value of the thread pointer in general-purpose
                register r13.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>TLS_TP_OFFSET</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The constant value 0x7000, representing the offset (in
                bytes) of the location that the thread pointer is initialized
                to point to, relative to the start of the thread local storage
                for the first initially available module.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>TCB_LENGTH</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The constant value 0x8, representing the length of the
                thread control block (TCB) in bytes.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>tcb</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the base address of the TCB.</para>
                <para>tcb = (tp - (TLS_TP_OFFSET + TCB_LENGTH))</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>dtv</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the base address of the dynamic thread vector
                (DTV).</para>
                <para>dtv = tcb[0]</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>dtpmod</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the load module index of the load module that
                contains the definition of the symbol being relocated and is
                used to index the DTV.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>dtprel</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the offset of the symbol being relocated
                relative to the value of dtv[dtpmod].</para>
                <para>dtv[dtpmod] + dtprel = (S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>tprel</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Represents the offset of the symbol being relocated
                relative to the TP.</para>
                <para>tp + tprel = (S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>tlsgd</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Allocates two contiguous entries in the GOT to hold a
                tls_index structure, with values dtpmod and dtprel, and
                computes the offset from .TOC. of the first entry.</para>
                <para>If n is the offset computed:</para>
                <para>GOT[n] = dtpmod</para>
                <para>GOT[n + 1] = dtprel</para>
                <para>The call to __tls_get_addr ( ) happens as:</para>
                <para>__tls_get_addr ((tls_index *) &amp;GOT[n])</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>tlsld</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Allocates two contiguous entries in the GOT to hold a
                tls_index structure, with values dtpmod and zero, and computes
                the offset from .TOC. of the first entry.</para>
                <para>If n is the offset computed:</para>
                <para>GOT[n] = dtpmod</para>
                <para>GOT[n + 1] = 0</para>
                <para>The call to __tls_get_addr ( ) happens as:</para>
                <para>__tls_get_addr ((tls_index *) &amp;GOT[n])</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>tprelg</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Allocates an entry in the GOT with value tprel, and
                computes the offset from .TOC. of the entry.</para>
                <para>If n is the offset computed:</para>
                <para>GOT[n] = tprel</para>
                <para>The value of tprel is loaded into a register from the
                location (GOT + n) to be used in an r2 form instruction.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <note>
        <para>Relocations flagged with an asterisk(*) will
        trigger a relocation failure if the value computed does
        not fit in the field specified.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Relocation Types Table</title>
      <para>The following rules apply to the relocation types defined in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_47572" />:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>For relocation types in which the names contain 14 or 16, the
          upper 49 bits of the value computed before shifting must all be the
          same. For relocation types in which the names contain 24, the upper
          39 bits of the value computed before shifting must all be the same.
          For relocation types in which the names contain 14 or 24, the low 2
          bits of the value computed before shifting must all be zero.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The relocation types whose Field column entry contains an
          asterisk (*) are subject to failure if the value computed does not
          fit in the allocated bits.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Relocations that refer to half16ds (56 - 66, 87 - 88, 91 - 92,
          95 - 96, and 101 - 102) are to be used to direct the linker to look
          at the underlying instruction and treat the field as a DS or DQ
          field. ABI-compliant tools should give an error for attempts to
          relocate an address to a value that is not divisible by 4.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_47572">
        <title>Relocation Table</title>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*" align="center" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="15*" align="center" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="15*" align="center" />
          <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="40*" align="center" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation Name</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Value</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Field</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Expression</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tfoot>
            <row>
              <entry nameend="c4" namest="c1" align="left">
                <note>
                  <para>Relocation values 8, 9, 12, 13, 18, 23, 32,
                      and 247 are not used. This is to maintain a
                      correspondence to the relocation values used by the
                      32-bit PowerPC ELF ABI.
                </para></note>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tfoot>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_NONE</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR32</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>word32*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>low24*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR14</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>7</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>low14*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>10</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>low24*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A - P) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL14</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>11</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>low14*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A - P) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>14</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>G</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>15</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(G)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(G)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>17</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(G)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_COPY</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>19</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>varies</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>See 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_90220" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GLOB_DAT</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>20</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_JMP_SLOT</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>21</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>See 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_90220" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_RELATIVE</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>22</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>B + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_UADDR32</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>word32*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_UADDR16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>25</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL32</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>26</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>word32*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A - P</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLT32</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>27</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>word32*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>L</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTREL32</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>28</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>word32*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>L - P</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLT16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>29</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(L)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLT16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(L)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLT16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>31</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(L)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_SECTOFF</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>33</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_SECTOFF_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>34</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(R + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_SECTOFF_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>35</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(R + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_SECTOFF_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>36</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(R + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>37</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>word30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A - P) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>38</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HIGHER</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>39</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#higher(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HIGHERA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>40</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highera(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HIGHEST</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>41</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highest(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HIGHESTA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>42</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highesta(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_UADDR64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>43</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>44</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A - P</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLT64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>45</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>L</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>46</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>L - P</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOC16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>47</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A - .TOC.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOC16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>48</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(S + A - .TOC.)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOC16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>49</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(S + A - .TOC.)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOC16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>50</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(S + A - .TOC.)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOC</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>51</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>.TOC.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTGOT16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>52</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>M</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTGOT16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>53</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(M)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTGOT16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>54</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(M)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTGOT16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>55</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(M)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>56</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>57</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(S + A) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>58</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>G &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>59</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(G) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLT16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>60</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(L) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_SECTOFF_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>61</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(R + A) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_SECTOFF_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>62</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(R + A) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOC16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>63</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A - .TOC.) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOC16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(S + A - .TOC.) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTGOT16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>65</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>M &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_PLTGOT16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>66</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(M) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>67</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPMOD64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>68</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@dtpmod</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>69</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@tprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>70</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>71</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>72</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>73</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@tprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>74</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@dtprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>75</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>76</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>77</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>78</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@dtprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>79</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@got@tlsgd</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>80</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@got@tlsgd)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>81</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(@got@tlsgd)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>82</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(@got@tlsgd)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>83</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@got@tlsld</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>84</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@got@tlsld)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>85</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(@got@tlsld)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>86</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(@got@tlsld)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>87</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@got@tprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>88</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@got@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>89</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(@got@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>90</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(@got@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>91</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@got@dtprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>92</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@got@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>93</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(@got@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>94</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(@got@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>95</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@tprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>96</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HIGHER</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>97</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#higher(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HIGHERA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>98</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highera(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HIGHEST</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>99</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highest(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HIGHESTA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>100</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highesta(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>101</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>@dtprel</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>102</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16ds</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HIGHER</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>103</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#higher(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HIGHERA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>104</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highera(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HIGHEST</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>105</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highest(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HIGHESTA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>106</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#highesta(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLSGD</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>107</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLSLD</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>108</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TOCSAVE</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>109</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>none</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HIGH</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>110</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#high(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR16_HIGHA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>111</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#higha(S + A)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HIGH</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>112</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#high(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HIGHA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>113</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#higha(@tprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HIGH</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>114</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#high(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HIGHA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>115</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#higha(@dtprel)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL24_NOTOC</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>116</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>low24*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(S + A - P) &gt;&gt; 2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_ADDR64_LOCAL</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>117</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A (See 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_90220" />.)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_IRELATIVE</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>248</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>doubleword64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>See 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_90220" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>249</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>S + A - P</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>250</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#lo(S + A - P)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL16_HI</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>251</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#hi(S + A - P)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>252</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>half16*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>#ha(S + A - P)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GNU_VTINHERIT</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>253</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GNU_VTENTRY</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>254</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_90220">
      <title>Relocation Descriptions</title>
      <para>The following list describes relocations that can require special
      handling or description.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_GOT16*</para>
      <para>These relocation types are similar to the corresponding
      R_PPC64_ADDR16* types. However, they refer to the address of the symbolâ€™s
      GOT entry and instruct the link editor to build a GOT.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_PLTGOT16*</para>
      <para>These relocation types are similar to the corresponding
      R_PPC64_GOT16* types. However, if the link editor 
      <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> determine the actual value of the symbol, the
      GOT entry may contain the address of an entry in the procedure linkage
      table. The link editor creates that entry in the procedure linkage table
      and stores that address in the GOT entry. This permits lazy resolution of
      function symbols at run time. If the link editor 
      <emphasis>can</emphasis> determine the value of the symbol, it stores that
      value in the corresponding GOT entry. The link editor may generate an
      R_PPC64_GLOB_DAT relocation as usual.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_PLTREL32, R_PPC64_PLTREL64</para>
      <para>These relocations indicate that reference to a symbol should be
      resolved through a call to the symbolâ€™s procedure linkage table entry.
      Additionally, it instructs the link editor to build a procedure linkage
      table for the executable or shared object if one is not created.</para>
      <para><anchor xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_R_PPC_COPY" xreflabel="" />R_PPC64_COPY</para>
      <para>This relocation type is created by the link editor for dynamic
      linking. Its offset member refers to a location in a writable segment.
      The symbol table index specifies a symbol that should exist both in the
      current relocatable file and in a shared object file. During execution,
      the dynamic linker copies data associated with the shared objectâ€™s symbol
      to the location specified by the offset.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_GLOB_DAT</para>
      <para>This relocation type allows determination of the correspondence
      between symbols and GOT entries. It is similar to R_PPC64_ADDR64.
      However, it sets a GOT entry to the address of the specified
      symbol.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_JMP_SLOT</para>
      <para>This relocation type is created by the link editor for dynamic
      linking. Its offset member gives the location of a procedure linkage
      table (PLT) entry. The dynamic linker modifies the PLT entry to transfer
      control to the designated symbolâ€™s address (see 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655242_20388" />).</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_RELATIVE</para>
      <para>This relocation type is created by the link editor for dynamic
      linking. Its offset member gives a location within a shared object that
      contains a value representing a relative address. The corresponding
      virtual address is computed by the dynamic linker. It adds the virtual
      address at which the shared object was loaded to the relative address.
      Relocation entries for this type must specify 0 for the symbol table
      index.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_IRELATIVE</para>
      <para>The link editor creates this relocation type for dynamic linking.
      Its addend member specifies the global entry-point location of a resolver
      function returning a function pointer. It is used to implement the
      STT_GNU_IFUNC framework. The resolver is called, and the returned pointer
      copied into the location specified by the relocation offset
      member.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_TLS, R_PPC64_TLSGD, R_PPC64_TLSLD</para>
      <para>Used as markers on thread local storage (TLS) code sequences, these
      relocations tie the entire sequence with a particular TLS symbol. For
      more information, see 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_90241" />.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_TOCSAVE</para>
      <para>This relocation type indicates a position where a TOC save may be
      inserted in the function to avoid a TOC save as part of the PLT stub
      code. A nop can be emitted by a compiler in a function's prologue code. A
      link editor can change it to a TOC pointer save instruction. This marker
      relocation is placed on the prologue nop and on nops after bl
      instructions, with the symbol plus addend pointing to the prologue nop.
      If the link editor uses the prologue to save r2, it may omit r2 saves in
      the PLT call stub code emitted for calls marked by
      R_PPC64_TOCSAVE.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_UADDR*</para>
      <para>These relocation types are the same as the corresponding
      R_PPC64_ADDR* types, except that the datum to be relocated is allowed to
      be unaligned.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_ADDR64_LOCAL</para>
      <para>When a separate local entry point exists, this relocation type is
      used to initialize a memory location with the address of that local entry
      point.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_REL24_NOTOC</para>
      <para>This relocation type is used to specify a function call where the
      TOC pointer is not initialized. It is similar to R_PPC64_REL24 in that it
      specifies a symbol to be resolved. However, if the symbol is resolved by
      inserting a call to a PLT stub code, the PLT stub code must not rely on
      the presence of a valid TOC base address in TOC register r2 to reference
      the PLT function table.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Assembler Syntax</title>
      <para>The offset from .TOC. in the GOT where the value of the symbol is
      stored is given by the assembly syntax symbol@got. The value of the
      symbol alone is the address of the variable named symbol.</para>
      <para>For example:</para>
      <programlisting>addis  r3, r2,x@got@ha
ld     r3,x@got@l(r3)</programlisting>
      <para>Although the Power ISA only defines 16-bit displacements, many TOCs
      (and hence a GOT) are larger then 64 KB but fit within 2 GB, which can be
      addressed with 32-bit offsets from r2. Therefore, this ABI defines a
      simple syntax for 32-bit offsets to the GOT.</para>
      <para>The syntaxes SYMBOL@got@ha, SYMBOL@got@h, and SYMBOL@got@l refer to
      the high adjusted, high, and low parts of the GOT offset. (For an
      explanation of the meaning of â€œhigh adjusted,â€ see
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_18894" />). SYMBOL@got@ha corresponds to
      bits 32 - 63 of the offset within the global offset table with adjustment
      for the sign extension of the low-order offset bits. SYMBOL@got@l
      corresponds to the 16 low-order bits of the offset within the global
      offset table.</para>
      <para>The syntax SYMBOL@toc refers to the value (SYMBOL - .TOC.), where
      .TOC. represents the TOC base for the current object file. This provides
      the address of the variable whose name is SYMBOL as an offset from the
      TOC base.</para>
      <para>As with the GOT, the syntaxes SYMBOL@toc@ha, SYMBOL@toc@h, and
      SYMBOL@toc@l refer to the high adjusted, high, and low parts of the TOC
      offset.</para>
      <para>The syntax SYMBOL@got@plt may be used to refer to the offset in the
      TOC of a procedure linkage table entry stored in the global offset table.
      The corresponding syntaxes SYMBOL@got@plt@ha, SYMBOL@got@plt@h, and
      SYMBOL@got@plt@l are also defined.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <note>
        <para>
        If X is a variable stored in the TOC,
        then X@got is the offset within the TOC of a doubleword whose
        value is X@toc.</para>
      </note>
      <para>The special symbol .TOC. is used to represent the TOC base for the
      current object file.</para>
      <para>The following code might appear in a PIC code setup sequence to
      compute the distance from a function entry point to the TOC base:</para> 
      <programlisting>addis  2,12,.TOC.-func@ha
addi   2,2,.TOC.-func@l</programlisting>      
      <para>The syntax 
      <literal>SYMBOL@localentry</literal> refers to the value of the local
      entry point associated with a function symbol. It can be used to
      initialize a memory word with the address of the local entry point as
      follows:</para>
      <programlisting>.quad  func@localentry</programlisting>      
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Assembler- and Linker-Mediated Executable Optimization</title>
    <para>To optimize object code, the assembler and linker may rewrite object
    code to implement the function call and return conventions and access to
    global and thread-local data. It is the responsibility of compilers and
    programmers to generate assembly programs and objects that conform to the
    requirements as indicated in this section.</para>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_69294">
      <title>Function Call</title>
      <para>The static linker must modify a nop instruction after a bl function
      call to restore the TOC pointer in r2 from 24(r1) when an external symbol
      that may use the TOC may be called, as in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655240_88555" />. Object files must contain a
      nop slot after a bl instruction to an external symbol.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Reference Optimization</title>
      <para>References to the GOT may be optimized by rewriting indirect
      reference code to replace the reference by an address computation. This
      transformation is only performed by the linker when the symbol is known
      to be local to the module.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Displacement Optimization for TOC Pointer Relative
      Accesses</title>
      <para>Assemblers and linkers 
      <emphasis>may</emphasis> optimize TOC reference code that consists of two
      instructions with equivalent code when offset@ha is 0.</para>
      <para>TOC reference code:</para>
      <programlisting>addis  rt, r2, offset@ha
lwz    rt, offset@l(rt)</programlisting>      
      <para>Equivalent code:</para>
      <programlisting>NOP
lwz    rt, offset(r2)</programlisting>      
      <para>Compilers and programmers 
      <emphasis>must</emphasis> ensure that r2 is live at the actual data access
      point associated with extended displacement addressing.</para>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_19147">
        <title>TOC Pointer Usage</title>
        <para>To enable linker-based optimizations when global data is accessed,
        the TOC pointer needs to be available for dereference at the point of all
        uses of values derived from the TOC pointer in conjunction with the @l
        operator. This property is used by the linker to optimize TOC pointer
        accesses. In addition, all reaching definitions for a TOC-pointer-derived
        access must compute the same definition.</para>
        <para>In some implementations, non-ABI-compliant code may be processed by
        providing additional linker options; for example, linker options
        disabling linker optimization. However, this behavior in support of
        non-ABI-compliant code is not guaranteed to be portable and supported in
        all systems.</para>
        <para>&#160;</para>
        <bridgehead>Compliant example</bridgehead>
        <programlisting>        addis  r4, r2, mysym@toc@ha
        b      target
 
 
        ...
 

        addis  r4, r2, mysym@toc@ha
target:
        addi   r4, r4, mysym@toc@l
        ...</programlisting>
        <para>&#160;</para>
        <bridgehead>Non-compliant example</bridgehead>
        <programlisting>               li     r4, 0 ; #d1
        b      target
 
        ...
 
        addis  r4, r2, mysym@toc@ha ; #d2
target:
        addi   r4, r4, mysym@toc@l ; incompatible definitions #d1 and #d2 reach this
        ...</programlisting>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Table Jump Sequences</title>
        <para>Some linkers may rewrite jump table sequences, as described in 
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655240_47036" />. For example, linkers may
        rewrite address references created using GOT-indirect loads and bl+4
        sequences to use TOC-relative address computation.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
      
    <section>
      <title>Fusion</title>
      <para>Code generation in compilers, linkers, and by programmers should
      use a destructive sequence of two sequential instructions consisting of
      first an addis followed by a second instruction using a D form
      instruction to create or load from a 32-bit offset from a register to
      enable hardware fusion whenever possible:</para>
      <programlisting>addis     r4, r3, upper
&lt;lbz,lhz,lwz,ld&gt; r4, lower(r4)
 
addis     r4, r3, upper
addi      r4, r4, lower</programlisting>
      <para>It is encouraged that assemblers provide pseudo-ops to facilitate
      such code generation with a single assembler mnemonic.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Thread-Local Linker Optimizations</title>
      <para>Additional code rewriting is performed by the linker in conjunction
      with the use of thread-local storage described in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_61284" />.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_90241">
    <title>Thread Local Storage ABI</title>
    <para>The 
    <citetitle>ELF Handling for Thread-Local Storage</citetitle> document is the
    authoritative TLS ABI specification that defines the context in which
    information in the TLS section of this Power Architecture 64-bit ELF V2 ABI
    must be viewed. For information about how to access this document, see 
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655239___RefHeading___Toc377640569" />. To
    maintain congruence with that document, in this section the term module
    refers to an executable or shared object since both are treated
    similarly.</para>
    <section>
      <title>TLS Background</title>
      <para>Most C/C++ implementations support (as an extension to earlier
      versions of the language) the keyword __thread to be used as a
      storage-class specifier in variable declarations and definitions of data
      objects with thread storage duration. (The 2011 ISO C Standard uses
      _Thread_local as the keyword, while the 2011 ISO C++ Standard uses
      thread_local.) A variable declared in this manner is automatically
      allocated local to each thread. Its lifetime is defined to be the entire
      execution of the thread. Any initialization value is assigned once before
      thread startup.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_50444">
      <title>TLS Runtime Handling</title>
      <para>A thread-local variable is completely identified by the module in
      which it is defined, along with the offset of the variable relative to
      the start of the TLS block for the module. A module is referenced by its
      index (an integer starting with 1, which is assigned by the run-time
      environment) into the dynamic thread vector (DTV). The offset of the
      variable is kept in the st_value field of the TLS variableâ€™s symbol table
      entry.</para>
      <para>The TLS data structures follow variant I of the ELF TLS ABI. For
      the 64-bit PowerPC Architecture, the specific organization of the data
      structures is as follows.</para>
      <para>The thread control block (TCB) consists of the DTV, which is an
      8-byte pointer. An extended TCB may have additional
      implementation-specific fields; these fields are located 
      <emphasis>before</emphasis> the DTV pointer because the addresses are
      computed as negative offsets from the TCB address. The fields must never
      be rearranged for any reason.</para>
      <para>The current glibc extended TCB is:</para>
      <programlisting>typedef struct {
    /* Reservation for HWCAP data. */
        unsigned int hwcap2;
        unsigned int hwcap; /* not used in LE ABI */
 
    /* Indicate if HTM capable (ISA 2.07). */
        int tm_capable;
        int tm_pad;
 
    /* Reservation for dynamic system optimizer ABI. */
        uintptr_t dso_slot2;
        uintptr_t dso_slot1;
 
    /* Reservation for tar register (ISA 2.07). */
        uintptr_t tar_save;
 
    /* GCC split stack support. */
        void *__private_ss;
 
    /* Reservation for the event-based branching ABI. */
        uintptr_t ebb_handler;
        uintptr_t ebb_ctx_pointer;
        uintptr_t ebb_reserved1;
        uintptr_t ebb_reserved2;
        uintptr_t pointer_guard;
 
    /* Reservation for stack guard */
        uintptr_t stack_guard;
 
    /* DTV pointer */
        dtv_t *dtv;
    } tcbhead_t;</programlisting>
      <para>Modules that will not be unloaded will be present at startup time;
      the TLS blocks for these are created consecutively and immediately follow
      the TCB. The offset of the TLS block of an initially available module
      from the TCB remains fixed after program start.</para>
      <para>The tlsoffset(m) values for a module with index m, where m ranges 1
      - M, M being the total number of modules, are computed as follows:</para>
      <programlisting>tlsoffset(1) = round(16, align(1))
tlsoffset(m + 1) = round(tlsoffset(m) + tlssize(m), align(m + 1))</programlisting>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The function round( ) returns its first argument rounded up to
          the next multiple of its second argument:</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <programlisting>round(x, y) = y Ã— ceiling(x / y)</programlisting>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The function ceiling( ) returns the smallest integer greater
          than or equal to its argument, where n is an integer satisfying: n -
          1 &lt; x â‰¤ n:</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <programlisting>ceiling(x) = n</programlisting>
      <para>In the case of dynamic shared objects (DSO), TLS blocks are
      allocated on an as-needed basis, with the details of allocation
      abstracted away by the __tls_get_addr( ) function, which is used to
      retrieve the address of any TLS variable.</para>
      <para>The prototype for the __tls_get_addr( ) function, is defined as
      follows.</para>
      <programlisting>typedef struct
{
   unsigned long int ti_module;
   unsigned long int ti_offset;
} tls_index;
 
extern void *__tls_get_addr (tls_index *ti);</programlisting>
      <para>The thread pointer (TP) is held in r13 and is used to access the
      TCB. The TP is initialized to point 0x7000 bytes past the end of the TCB.
      The TP offset allows for efficient addressing of the TCB and up to 4 KB -
      8 B of other thread library information (placed before the TCB).</para>
      <para>
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_11666" /> shows the region of memory
      before and after the TCB that can be efficiently addressed by the
      TP.</para>
      <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_11666">
        <title>Thread Pointer Addressable Memory</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fig3-1.png" format="PNG"
            scalefit="1" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Each DTV pointer points 0x8000 bytes past the start of each TLS
      block. (For implementation reasons, the actual value stored in the DTV
      may point to the start of a TLS block. However, values returned by
      accessor functions will be offset by 0x8000 bytes.) This offset allows
      the first 64 KB of each block to be addressed from a DTV pointer using
      fewer machine instructions.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_25002">
        <title>TLS Block Diagram</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fig3-2.png" format="PNG"
            scalefit="1" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>TLS[m] denotes the TLS block for the module with index m. DTV[m]
      denotes the DTV pointer for the module with index m.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TLS Access Models</title>
      <para>TLS data access is categorized into the following models:</para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>General Dynamic TLS Model</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Local Dynamic TLS Model</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Initial Exec TLS Model</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Local Exec TLS Model</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Examples for each access model are provided in the following TLS
      Model subsections.</para>
    <section>
      <title>General Dynamic TLS Model</title>
      <note>
        <para>This specification provides examples based on the medium
        code model, which is the default for the ELF V2 ABI.</para>
      </note>
      <para>Given the following code fragment, to determine the address of a
      thread-local variable x, the __tls_get_addr( ) function is called with one
      parameter. That parameter is a pointer to a data object of type
      tls_index.</para>
      <programlisting>extern __thread unsigned int x;
&amp;x;</programlisting>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General Dynamic Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r2, x@got@tlsgd@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r3, r3, x@got@tlsgd@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="1">
                <para>bl __tls_get_addr(x@tlsgd)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLSGD</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>__tls_get_addr</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General Dynamic GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPMOD64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n+1]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The relocation specifier @got@tlsgd causes the link editor to
      create a data object of type tls_index in the GOT. The address of this
      data object is loaded into the first argument register with the addis and
      addi instruction, and a standard function call is made. Notice that the
      bl instruction has two relocations: the R_PPC64_TLSGD tying it to the
      argument setup instructions and the R_PPC64_REL24 specifying the call
      destination.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Local Dynamic TLS Model</title>
      <para>For the Local Dynamic TLS Model, three different relocation
      sequences may be used, depending on the size of the thread storage block
      offset to the variable. For the following code sequence, a different
      relocation sequence is used for each variable.</para>
      <programlisting>static __thread unsigned int x1;
static __thread unsigned int x2;
static __thread unsigned int x3;
&amp;x1;
&amp;x2;
&amp;x3;</programlisting>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_45768">
        <title>Local Dynamic Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r2, x1@got@tlsld@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r3, r3, x1@got@tlsld@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>bl __tls_get_addr(x1@tlsld)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLSLD</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>__tls_get_addr</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r3, x1@dtprel</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r3, x2@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r9, x2@dtprel@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r2, x3@got@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r9, x3@got@dtprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>add r9, r9, r3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Local Dynamic GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPMOD64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n+1]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[m]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The relocation specifier @got@tlsld in the first instruction causes
      the link editor to generate a tls_index data object in the GOT with a
      fixed 0 offset. The following code assumes that x1 is in the first 64 KB
      of the thread storage block. The x2 symbol is not within the first 64 KB
      but is within the first 2 GB, and x3 is outside the 2 GB area. To load
      the values of x1, x2, and x3 instead of their addresses, replace the
      latter part of 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_45768" /> with the following code
      sequence.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_48794">
        <title>Local Dynamic Relocations with Values Loaded</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>lwz r0, x1@dtprel(r3)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r3, x2@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>lwz r0, x2@dtprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r2, x3@got@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r9, x3@got@dtprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>lwzx r0, r3, r9</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Initial Exec TLS Model</title>
      <para>Given the following code fragment, the relocation sequence in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_17435" /> is used for the Initial Exec
      TLS Model:</para>
      <programlisting>extern __thread unsigned int x;
&amp;x;</programlisting>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_17435">
        <title>Initial Exec Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r2, x@got@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r9, x@got@tprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>add r9, r9, x@tls</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Initial Exec GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The relocation specifier @got@tprel in the first instruction causes
      the link editor to generate a GOT entry with a relocation that the
      dynamic linker will replace with the offset for x relative to the thread
      pointer. The relocation specifier x@tls tells the assembler to use an r13
      form of the instruction. That is, add r9,r9,r13 in this case, and tag the
      instruction with a relocation that indicates it belongs to a TLS
      sequence. This relocation specifier can be used later by the link editor
      when optimizing TLS code.</para>
      <para>To read the contents of the variable instead of calculating its
      address, the add r9, r9, x@tls instruction might be replaced with lwzx
      r0, r9, x@tls.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Local Exec TLS Model</title>
      <para>Given the following code fragment, three different relocation
      sequences may be used, depending on the size of the offset to the
      variable. The sequence in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_45954" /> handles offsets within 60 KB
      relative to the end of the TCB (where r13 points 28 KB past the end of
      the TCB, which is immediately before the first TLS block). The sequence
      in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_47421" /> handles offsets past 60 KB and
      less than 2 GB + 28 KB relative to the end of the TCB. The third sequence
      is identical to the Initial Exec sequence shown in
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_17435" />.</para>
      <programlisting>static __thread unsigned int x;
&amp;x;</programlisting>
      <para><xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_51121" /> illustrates which sequence is
      used.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <figure pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_51121">
        <title>Local Exec TLS Model Sequences</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fig3-3.png" format="PNG"
            scalefit="1" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_45954">
        <title>Local Exec Initial Relocations (Sequence 1)</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r13, x1@tprel</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC_TPREL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_47421">
        <title>Local Exec Initial Relocations (Sequence 2)</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r13, x2@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r9, x2@tprel@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_61284">
      <title>TLS Link Editor Optimizations</title>
      <para>In some cases, the link editor may be able to optimize TLS code
      sequences, provided the compiler emits code sequences as
      described.</para>
      <para>The following TLS link editor transformations are provided as
      optimizations to convert between specific TLS access models:</para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>General Dynamic to Initial Exec</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>General Dynamic to Local Exec</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Local Dynamic to Local Exec</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Initial Exec to Local Exec</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>General Dynamic to Initial Exec</title>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General-Dynamic-to-Initial-Exec Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r2, x@got@tlsgd@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r3, r3, x@got@tlsgd@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="1">
                <para>bl __tls_get_addr(x@tlsgd)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLSGD</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>__tls_get_addr</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General-Dynamic-to-Initial-Exec GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPMOD64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n+1]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The preceding code and global offset table entries are replaced by
      the following code and global offset table entries.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General-Dynamic-to-Initial-Exec Replacement Initial
        Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r2, x@got@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r3, x@got@tprel@l(r3)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>add r3, r3, r13</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General-Dynamic-to-Initial-Exec Replacement GOT Entry
        Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>General Dynamic to Local Exec</title>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General-Dynamic-to-Local-Exec Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r2, x@got@tlsgd@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r3, r3, x@got@tlsgd@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSGD16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="1">
                <para>bl __tls_get_addr(x@tlsgd)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLSGD</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>__tls_get_addr</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_16273">
        <title>General-Dynamic-to-Local-Exec GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPMOD64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n+1]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The preceding code and global offset table entries are replaced by
      the following code, which makes no reference to GOT entries. The GOT
      entries in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_16273" /> can be removed from the GOT by
      the linker when performing this code transformation.<footnote xml:id="pgfId-1134055">
        <para>To further optimize the code in 
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_16273" />, a linker may reschedule the
        sequence to exploit fusion by generating a sequence that may be fused
        by Power processors:</para>
      <programlisting>nop
addis  r3, r13, x@tprel@ha
addi   r3, r3, x@tprel@l
nop</programlisting>
      </footnote></para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>General-Dynamic-to-Local-Exec Replacement Initial
        Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r13, x@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r3, r3, x@tprel@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Local Dynamic to Local Exec</title>
      <para>Under this TLS linker optimization, the function call is replaced
      with an equivalent code sequence. However, as shown in the following code
      examples, the dtprel sequences are left unchanged.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_56118">
        <title>Local-Dynamic-to-Local-Exec Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r2, x1@got@tlsld@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r3, r3, x1@got@tlsld@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TLSLD16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>bl __tls_get_addr(x1@tlsld)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLSLD</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_REL24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>__tls_get_addr</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r3, x1@dtprel</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r3, x2@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r9, x2@dtprel@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r2, x3@got@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r9, x3@got@dtprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>add r9, r9, r3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Local-Dynamic-to-Local-Exec GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPMOD64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n+1]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[m]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <para>The preceding code and global offset table entries are replaced by
      the following code and global offset table entries.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Local-Dynamic-to-Local-Exec Replacement Initial
        Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r3, r13, L@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>link editor generated local symbol</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r3, r3, L@tprel@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>link editor generated local symbol<footnote>
		<para>The linker may prefer to schedule the addis and addi
		to be adjacent to take advantage of fusion as a
		microarchitecture optimization opportunity.</para></footnote>
		</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>..</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r3, x1@dtprel</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>..</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r3, x2@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r9, x2@dtprel@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x2</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>...</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r2, x3@got@dtprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r9, x3@got@dtprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_DTPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>add r9, r9, r3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The GOT[n] and GOT[n+1] entries can be removed by the linker after
      the code transformation as shown in 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_90771" />.</para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_90771">
        <title>Local-Dynamic-to-Local-Exec Replacement GOT Entry
        Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[m]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_DTPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x3</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The local symbol generated by the link editor points to the start
      of the thread storage block plus 0x7000 bytes. In practice, a section
      symbol with a suitable offset will be used.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Initial Exec to Local Exec</title>
      <para>This transformation is only performed by the linker when the symbol
      is within 2 GB + 28 KB of the thread pointer.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Initial-Exec-to-Local-Exec Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r2, x@got@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r9, x@got@tprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>add r9, r9, x@tls</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Initial-Exec-to-Local-Exec GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The preceding code and global offset table entries are replaced by
      the following code and global offset table entries.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Initial-Exec-to-Local-Exec Replacement Initial
        Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Code Sequence</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Relocation</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Symbol</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r13, x@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r9, r9, x@tprel@l</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>Other sizes and types of thread-local variables may use any of the
      X-form indexed load or store instructions.</para>
      <para>
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_81882" /> shows how to access the
      contents of a variable using the X-form indexed load and store
      instructions.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_81882">
        <title>Initial-Exec-to-Local-Exec X-form Initial Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r2, x@got@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>ld r9, x@got@tprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_GOT_TPREL16_LO_DS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>lbzx r10, r9, x@tls</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r10, r10, 1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>stbx r10, r9, x@tls</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TLS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Initial-Exec-to-Local-Exec X-form GOT Entry Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>GOT[n]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL64</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>The preceding code and global offset table entries are replaced by
      the following code and global offset table entries.</para>
      <para> </para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>Initial-Exec-to-Local-Exec X-form Replacement Initial
        Relocations</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="33*" />
          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Code Sequence</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Relocation</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Symbol</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>nop</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addis r9, r13, x@tprel@ha</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_HA</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>lbz r10, x@tprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>addi r10, r10, 1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para> </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>stb r10, x@tprel@l(r9)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>R_PPC64_TPREL16_LO</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>x</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>ELF TLS Definitions</title>
      <para>The result of performing a relocation for a TLS symbol is the
      module ID and its offset within the TLS block. These are then stored in
      the GOT. Later, they are obtained by the dynamic linker at run-time and
      passed to __tls_get_addr( ), which returns the address for the variable
      for the current thread.</para>
      <para>For more information, see 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_18894" />. For TLS relocations, see 
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_47572" />.</para>
      <para>&#160;</para>
      <bridgehead>TLS Relocation Descriptions</bridgehead>
      <para>The following marker relocations tie together instructions in TLS
      code sequences. They allow the link editor to reliably optimize TLS code.
      R_PPC64_TLSGD and R_PPC64_TLSLD shall be emitted immediately before their
      associated __tls_get_addr call relocation.</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_TLS</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_TLSGD</para>
      <para>R_PPC64_TLSLD</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>System Support Functions and Extensions</title>
    <section>
      <title>Back Chain</title>
      <para>Systems must provide a back chain by default, and they must include
      compilers allocating a back chain and system libraries allocating a back
      chain. Alternate libraries may be supplied in addition to, and beyond,
      but never instead of those providing a back chain. Code generating and
      using a back chain shall be the default for compilers, linkers, and
      library selection.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Nested Functions</title>
      <para>Nested functions that access their ancestorsâ€™ stack frames are
      entered with r11 initialized to an environment pointer. The environment
      pointer is typically a copy of the stack pointer for the most recent
      instance of the nested function's parent's stack frame. When a function
      pointer to a nested function referencing its outer context is created, an
      implementation may create a trampoline to load the present environment
      pointer to r11, followed by an unconditional branch to the function code
      of the nested function contained in the text segment.</para>
      <para>When a trampoline is used, a pointer to a nested function is
      represented by the code address of the trampoline.</para>
      <para>In some environments, the trampoline code may be created by
      allocating memory on the data stack, making at least pages containing
      trampolines executable. In other environments, executable pages may be
      prohibited in the stack area for security reasons.</para>
      <para>Alternate implementations, such as creating code stacks for
      allocating nested function trampolines, may be used. In garbage-collected
      environments, yet other ways for managing trampolines are
      available.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Traceback Tables</title>
      <para>To support debuggers and exception handlers, the 64-bit 
      <citetitle>OpenPOWER ELF V2 ABI</citetitle> defines the use of descriptive
      debug and unwind information that enables flexible debugging and
      unwinding of optimized code (such as, for example, DWARF).</para>
      <para>To support legacy tooling, the 
      <citetitle>OpenPOWER ELF V2 ABI</citetitle> also specifies the use of a
      traceback table that may provide additional information about
      functions.</para>
      <para>
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655241_18645" /> describes a minimal set of
      fields that may, optionally, specify information about a function.
      Additional fields may be present in a traceback table in accordance with
      commonly used PowerPC traceback conventions in other environments, but
      they are not specified in the current ABI definition.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50655241_18645">
      <title>Traceback Table Fields</title>
      <para>If a traceback table is present, the following fields are
      mandatory:</para>
      <para> </para>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="15*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="85*" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>version</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Eight-bit field. This defines the type code for the
                table. The only currently defined value is zero.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>lang</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Eight-bit field. This defines the source language for the
                compiler that generated the code to which this traceback table
                applies. The default values are as follows:</para>
                <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                  <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="15*" />
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="85*" />
                    <tbody>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>C</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>0</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Fortran</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>1</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Pascal</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>2</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Ada</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>3</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>PL/1</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>4</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Basic</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>5</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>LISP</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>6</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>COBOL</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>7</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Modula2</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>8</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>C++</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>9</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>RPG</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>10</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>PL.8, PLIX</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>11</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Assembly</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>12</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Java</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>13</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry><para>Objective C</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>14</para></entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry nameend="c2" namest="c1">
                           <para>The codes 0xf - 0xfa are reserved. The codes 
                              0xfb - 0xff are reserved for IBM.</para></entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>globalink</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if this routine is
                a special routine used to support the linkage convention: a
                linkage function including a procedure linkage table function,
                pointer glue code, a trampoline, or other compiler- or
                linker-generated functions that stack traceback functions
                should skip, other than is_eprol functions. For more
                information, see 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655240_88555" />. These routines have
                an unusual register usage and stack format.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>is_eprol</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if this routine is
                an out-of-line prologue or epilogue function, including a
                register save or restore function. Stack traceback functions
                should skip these. For more information, see 
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50655240_12107" />. These routines have
                an unusual register usage and stack format.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>has_tboff</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the offset of
                the traceback table from the start of the function is stored in
                the tb_offset field.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>int_proc</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if this function is
                a stackless leaf function that does not have a separate stack
                frame.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>has_ctl</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if ctl_info is
                provided.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>tocless</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if this function
                does not have a TOC. For example, a stackless leaf assembly
                language routine with no references to external objects.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>fp_present</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the function
                uses floating-point processor instructions.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>log_abort</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. Reserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>int_handl</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. Reserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>name_present</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the name for the
                procedure is present following the traceback field, as
                determined by the name_len and name fields.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>uses_alloca</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the procedure
                performs dynamic stack allocation. To address their local
                variables, these procedures require a different register to
                hold the stack pointer value. This register may be chosen by
                the compiler, and must be indicated by setting the value of the
                alloc_reg field.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>cl_dis_inv</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Three-bit field. Reserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>saves_cr</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field indicates whether the CR fields
                are saved in the CR save word. If traceback tables are used in
                place of DWARF unwind information, at least all volatile CR
                fields must be saved in the CR save word.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>saves_lr</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the function
                saves the LR in the LR save doubleword.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>stores_bc</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the function
                saves the back chain (the SP of its caller) in the stack frame
                header.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>fixup</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the link editor
                replaced the original instruction by a branch instruction to a
                special fix-up instruction sequence.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>fp_saved</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Six-bit field. This field is set to the number of
                nonvolatile floating-point registers that the function saves.
                When traceback unwind and debug information is used, the last
                register saved is always f31. Therefore, for example, a value
                of 2 in this field indicates that f30 and f31 are saved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>has_vec_info</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if the procedure
                saves nonvolatile vector registers in the Vector Register Save
                Area, specifies the number of vector parameters, or uses VMX
                instructions.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>spare4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. Reserved.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>gpr_saved</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Six-bit field. This field is set to the number of
                nonvolatile general registers that the function saves. As with
                fp_saved, when traceback unwind and debug information is used,
                the last register saved is always r31.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>fixedparms</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Eight-bit field. This field is set to the number of
                fixed-point parameters.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>floatparms</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Seven-bit field. This field is set to the number of
                floating-point parameters.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>parmsonstk</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>One-bit field. This field is set to 1 if all of the
                parameters are placed in the Parameter Save Area.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para> </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
